Part One: Nutrition Challenges
No matter how complete your diet
and caloric intake is,
you will likely still lose weight
throughout your treatment due
to side effects caused by radiation exposure.
The first challenge to nutrition,
from radiation treatment
to the head and neck is the loss of taste.
This side effect will last
the entirety of treatment,
and it will take several months to fully
come back,
potentially up to six months or more.
Being unable to taste foods
the way you could before
will decrease your appetite
and desire to eat.
The second challenge is swelling
or irritation of the mucosa
or lining of the head
and neck, caused by radiation.
This effect is called mucositis.
Mucositis,
or inflammation of the sensitive mucosa
lining the mouth and esophagus will occur.
The esophagus is the tube carrying food
from your mouth down to your stomach.
Inflammation of these tissues is painful
and can make it more difficult
to chew and swallow food.
These two issues are the main challenges to good nutrition
throughout head and neck radiation treatment.
Other possible setbacks include nausea.
If you are receiving chemotherapy
in conjunction with radiation
or recent surgical procedures
that make it more difficult
to physically swallow food.
Unfortunately,
these challenges are unavoidable,
but there are actions you can
take to make your treatment
and journey towards being cancer free
as smooth and painless as possible.
This includes avoiding spicy foods,
acidic or sour foods
such as orange juice and alcohol.
These foods and liquids will irritate
and burn
the already
irritated tissues of the throat and mouth.